バイバ～イ
See ya.
See you tomorrow.
じゃ また 明日ね
何 あれ？
何だ？
もう帰らなきゃ
We really have to go home now.
んじゃあ 引き分けだね
Let’s call it a draw then.
ずるい！ もうちょっとで
こっちが 勝つのに…
That’s not fair!
We were just about to win!
You guys should surrender.
アンタたち 降伏しなさいよ
Yeah! We were way better.
そうだよ！
こっちの方が 優勢なんだから
降伏って なんなのよ！
Surrender? What are you talking about?
だって こっちが優勢じゃんか
We were better, right?
旗も 取られてないのに
降伏なんかするわけないでしょ！
You don’t even have the flag.
Why on Earth would we surrender?
引き分けだな
A draw, I’d say.
覚！
あなた 何で向こうの肩 持つの
Satoru! Why are you siding with them now?
ルールだよ ルール
しょうがないだろ
Rules, I tell you. Rules.
Gotta follow them.
日没 時間切れ
Time’s up when the sun goes down.
まだ 太陽あるじゃない！
But it’s still right there!
ここだから見えるだけじゃん！
Only because we’re up on a hill.
真理亜ちゃん もう帰らなきゃ
Let’s go home, Maria-chan.
We have to go home once we hear Going Home…
｢家路｣が聞こえてきたら
すぐに帰らないと
We could go home right now if you surrender.
そっちが 降伏すりゃ
すぐ帰れるよ
お前ら… おい！ 審判！
You guys…
Hey, referee!
Yeah?
Take this seriously.
うん？ じゃねぇよ！
The referee wasn’t even paying attention.
Tell them it’s a draw.
審判が ちゃんと引き分けって
言えよ！
判定してくれよ！
Come on.
You’re right.
そうだな 今日は引き分けだ
It’s a draw.
ちょっと 瞬！
Hey, Shun!
We’re going home!
私たち もう帰るからね
Wait for us!
待ってよ！
まだ 終わってないのに…
We weren’t done!
I’m going now! The Copycats will come.
帰る！
だって ネコダマシ出るもん
早季～！ 俺らも帰ろう
Saki, let’s go!
あそこ 見える？
Can you see that?
あっ… 何？
See what?
ミノシロ
A minoshiro.
Yeah.
So? What’s so special about it?
んだよ！ 別に珍しくないだろ！
A thousand years later
Ibaraki, Kamisu 66th District
FROM
THE
NEW
WORLD
The Season
of New
Leaves
私は この破れ寺の
和尚をしております
I am Mushin, the head priest of this ravaged temple.
無瞋と申します
あっ… 渡辺早季です
I’m Watanabe Saki.
あの ここ… ここは？
Um… Where… Where am I?
この寺は 清浄寺といいます
This temple is called the Temple of Purity.
あの… 八丁標の外なんですか？
Um, is this outside the Holy Barrier?
そうです
あなたは 生まれて初めて
It is.
You have ventured outside the Holy Barrier for the first time in your life.
八丁標の外へ 出たことになります
それでは これより
Now then, let us kindle cedar sticks for your passage to adulthood.
成長の護摩をたきます
Let us burn away the last of your worldly desires.
煩悩の 最後の１つを
焼き尽くしましょう
炎を見なさい
Look at the flames.
炎を 操ってみなさい
Try controlling them.
I can’t.
できません…
大丈夫 できます
炎を揺らしてみるのです
Fear not. You can.
Make the flames tremble.
Sway them from left to right.
左に 右に ゆらゆらと…
きゃあ！ はっ…
Saki!
早季！ もう大丈夫よ！
Everything is okay now!
何これ…
What is this?!
A Spirit of Blessing.
祝霊よ！ とうとう
あなたにも やってきたの
It has come to you too!
これが？
This?
It means you’re an adult now.
これで 早季も
大人になったっていうことだよ
You’ve graduated from Harmony School!
和貴園は 今日で卒業よ
全人学級に入るの
You’ll be in Sage Academy now!
ああ よかった！
I’m so happy!
もう 何も心配いらないからね！
We don’t have to worry anymore!
そこまで！ やめなさい！
Stop! That’s enough!
最後に 残された煩悩とは
The last worldly desire left within you is your Cantus itself.
あなたの その呪力です
煩悩を捨てなさい
Cast away your worldly attachments.
解脱のためには
You must cast all of them into the
purging flames to reach enlightenment.
すべてを
いったん 清浄な炎の中で
焼き尽くさなければなりません
天から授かった能力は
神仏に お返ししましょう
Let us give the power that the heavens granted you back to the gods.
今から あなたの呪力を
We shall seal your Cantus in this human emblem.
この人形の中に 封じ込めます
人形を操って 立たせなさい
Control the emblem and make it stand.
その人形に ありったけの思いを
込めるのです
Put all your feelings, everything, into this emblem.
渡辺早季！
Watanabe Saki!
お前の呪力は ここに封印された！
Your Cantus has been sealed here!
All your worldly desires have been burned away, and the ash will return to the ravaged earth.
全ての煩悩を 焼き尽せしめ
灰は 無辺の荒土に返るべし
あなたの呪力は 消滅しました
Your Cantus has been eradicated.
炎を見なさい
Look at the flames.
You can no longer control the flames.
あなたには
もはや 炎を操ることはできません
あなたは 深く神仏に帰依し
You have shown great devotion and abandoned your Cantus.
自ら 呪力を ほうてきしました
されば ここに
正しきマントラを授け
Now I shall teach you a pure mantra, summon a
new spirit and bestow Cantus upon you once more.
新たな精霊を 招へいし
再度 呪力を付与します
マントラ…
Mantra…
今日から
皆さんのクラスメートになる
This is Watanabe Saki-san, your new classmate.
渡辺早季さんです
Watanabe          Saki
俺たち １班だ
We’re all in Group I.
守は 友愛園
Mamoru’s from Friendship School.
こんにちは
Hello.
Nice to meet you.
よろしく
よろしくね
Nice to meet you too!
Took you a while.
遅かったね
ごめん 待たせちゃった
Sorry I took so long.
You bet!
ホントよ！
待ちくたびれちゃったわ
We got tired of waiting.
あたし 大器晩成なのよ
I’m a late bloomer.
別に 早くやって来た祝霊が
いいとは限らないし
It’s not like it’s necessarily a good thing if the spirit comes to you quickly.
にしても 和貴園組じゃ ビリ
So you say, and still you’re the last one.
いくら何でも のんびりしすぎ
Say what you want, but you sure took your time.
Oh come on, Satoru! You weren’t much faster!
覚だって
ほとんど 変わんないじゃん！
えっ？ ビリ？
Wait, the last?
何 言ってんの？
私の他にも まだ何人もいたよ？
But the class that I left still has a lot of kids.
May you be cleansed within.
みそぎをうちに
Well…
それは…
全人学級には
学科だけじゃなくて
In Sage Academy, we practice our abilities on top of covering the normal subjects.
能力実技があるのよ
Did anyone tell you?
知ってる？ 私 波紋干渉じゃ
クラスでトップの成績なの
I’m top of the class in Surface Water Manipulation.
撃力交換の方は
全然 ダメダメだけどな
And you’re a complete failure
when it comes to Force Exchange.
The teacher said I should focus on the imaging part of it for the time being!
今は まだ
イメージングの方が大事だって
先生は 言ってたわ！
あっ… 妙法農場だ
The Lotus Farms.
This place is similar.
ここ あそこに似てる
どこ？
To where?
Don’t you remember? We went on a field trip in Harmony School.
ほら 和貴園の時
見学に行ったじゃん
Wow.
すっげえ…
あっ
あれ フクロウシじゃないかな？
Hey, aren’t those pouchcows?
えっ？ ホントだわ！ 袋がある！
You’re right!
They’ve got pouches!
うっへえ～！
ここが 似てる？ 何 言ってんの？
This place is similar?
What are you on about?
なんだか
雰囲気が そっくりだってこと
The atmosphere just reminded me of it.
意味 分かんねえ
No idea what you’re talking about.
Hey, Saki.
早季！ ２時間目は
悪鬼と業魔の授業よ
Next period is Fiends and Karma Demons.
ええ… まだやるの？
What? We still have that?
I don’t like that subject.
私 あれ あんまり好きじゃない
Unlike back in Harmony School,
we’re reading the unabridged version!
和貴園のときとは違って
完全版なの
ふ～ん…
では 今日は 秋月さん
Fiend
Very well, Akizuki-san will read today.
はい！
Yes, sir.
LOGIC
今から 500年ほど前の話
It was about five hundred years ago.
LOGIC
山の中で
薬草を採っていた少年がいた
LOGIC
A young man was wandering the mountains, picking herbs.
夢中になって探しているうちに
Completely absorbed in his herb-picking, he reached the Holy Barrier.
八丁標の しめ縄の前にやってきた
ふと 目をやると 外側には
He glanced outside the cordon and saw a large field of herbs.
まだ たくさんの薬草が
残っているのが見えた
以前から 絶対に
八丁標の外に出てはいけないと
He had been reminded many times by adults that crossing the Holy Barrier was forbidden.
大人に クギを刺されていた
If the need arose for whatever reason,
he was supposed to be accompanied by an adult.
どうしても 必要がある時は
大人に伴われて
出なくてはならないのだ
向こうから
悪鬼が やってくるのが見えた
He saw a fiend coming for him.
悪鬼は 自分に
村まで案内させようとしている
He was about to lead the fiend back to his village.
このままでは…
If he followed the path to the village, the fiend would surely obliterate it.
このまま
悪鬼を連れて 村に戻れば
村は 全滅してしまう
どうすればいいのだろう
What should he do?
僕の命は
どうなっても かまいません
“My life matters not.”
“The fiend should never find the village.”
どうか 悪鬼を
村に近づけないで下さい
それ以来 今日に至るまで
And so, no fiend has ever found our village so far.
Fiend
悪鬼は 一度も現れていない
よくできました はい！
では 皆さん 最初のﾍﾟｰｼﾞに戻って…
Well done, thank you.
Now, everyone.
Go back to the first page and read…
ふん！
Look at it carefully.
よ～く 見てくださいね～
細かい所も しっかりと
イメージしてください
Picture the fine details too.
作者の 心の投影が
見えてきたりしますよ
Try to see the artist’s own mental projection.
はい
うん
Here.
うわ… 瞬 すごいね
That’s amazing, Shun.
Here.
はい
You’re so fast!
はえ～な～
I can beat that!
楽勝！
しゃ！ はい 守！
Here, Mamoru!
Okay.
できた 真理亜だよ
Done. Here, Maria.
うん 任せて
Okay, here I go.
はい う～ん いい出来
All right! That’s good work.
最後 麗子よ
You’re up last, Reiko.
Okay.
頼むぜ～ 麗子
We’re counting on you, Reiko.
I’ll do my best.
うん 頑張る…
あ！
あっちゃ～
ごめんなさい！
I’m sorry!
気にすることないよ
Don’t worry. Let’s just try again.
もう１回 最初から頑張ろ
ごめんなさい…
I’m sorry.
I’m not going to lose to you.
負けねえぞ…
You’re mighty slow.
もっと ペース上がんねえのかよ
You’re not much faster!
いい勝負じゃない！ アンタには
負けないから 安心してください
I’m not going to lose to you anyway, so don’t worry.
バ～カ！ 班の中で
競争しても しょうがねえだろ
You idiot. Racing amongst ourselves isn’t going to earn us anything.
見ろよ ５班
Look at Group V.
めちゃくちゃ 調子いいんだよ
They work really well together.
Our ace is in perfect shape, though.
相変わらず
エースは絶好調なんだけどな
でもな～ 足を引っ張っちゃう人も
いるからな
But well…
We also have people dragging us down.
麗子がいるかぎり
うちの班の優勝はないな
We’ll never win anything with Reiko here.
はあ？ 麗子は いい子よ！
Reiko’s a nice girl!
ただ ちょっと調子が出ないだけ！
She’s just a little below par today.
バカじゃないの！
ああ？
Are you stupid?
I’m sorry. I’m so sorry.
ごめんなさい
ホント ごめんなさい！
悪い 悪い
ごめんなさい ごめんなさい…
Oops, my bad.
I’m sorry. I’m sorry.
ふざけてんじゃねえぞ！ コラ！
冗談じゃないわよ！
ねえ
なんで麗子 誘わなかったの？
Hey, why didn’t you invite Reiko?
配慮だよ 配慮 配慮
I’m trying to be considerate here. Considerate.
あんなん なったあとだぜ？
You saw what happened today.
一緒に帰ったら
アイツの方が いたたまれねえって
Walking home with us would only hurt her more.
ふ～ん
But man, she was apologizing too much.
…にしたって 謝りすぎなんだよ
イヤんなってくるよ
It was embarrassing.
そういうこと言わない！
Don’t say that!
だって そうじゃん？
Well, that’s how it is.
We’re all pretty talented.
俺らの１班は 能力 高いんだぜ
瞬もいるしさ なあ 瞬
We’ve got Shun too.
Right, Shun?
いや 僕… そんなことないよ
I’m not that great.
You are.
そうだって！
いつも 麗子が失敗すっから
It’s always Reiko who screws up.
We’re never going to win.
何かったって 優勝できねえんだ
みんなも そう思ってんだろ？
I know you all agree with me.
ねえ 和貴園を卒業しないで
Hey, I heard there are people who never graduate from Harmony School and just disappear.
途中で いなくなる人もいるって
聞いたことあるんだけど…
早季 それは ただのウワサだよ
That’s just a rumor, Saki.
But, I mean…
でもさあ
みんな 気になんないの？
Doesn’t it bother you?
ウワサだけどさ 聞いたことがある
I’ve heard something, but it’s just a rumor.
Harmony
School
先生たちがさあ
The only time you can catch a glimpse of what’s inside that door is when the teachers open it.
あの扉を開けるときだけ
中庭が ちらっと見えんじゃん？
そこにさ… すげえ たくさんの
お墓があったんだって
And there are lots of graves inside…
ウソ
怖い…
Lies.
That’s scary.
Are you telling tall tales again?
また ホラ話？
それ 誰のお墓なの？
Whose graves are those?
そんなん知るか とにかく
ものすごく たくさんの…
How would I know?
But there were, like, so many—
Why would they have to put up gravestones inside the school?
何で わざわざ
学校の中庭なんかに
お墓を作らなきゃなんないの？
バカじゃないの？
Are you stupid or something?
んだよ！
そこまで知らねえって！
What’s your problem? How am I supposed to know?
There weren’t any graves.
お墓なんて なかったよ
えっ？
You’ve seen what’s inside, Shun?
瞬 見たの？
Remember the time when the teacher had trouble collecting everyone’s homework?
前にさ 宿題の答案が なかなか
集まらなかったことがあったよね
理科の自由観察
先生に｢全員のをまとめてから
The independent observation one for science.
The teacher told me to gather it all and bring it to him, so I went into the administrative wing.
持って来なさい｣って言われて
僕は管理棟に入ったんだ…
そこから 中庭は見えたけど
あそこに並んでたのは
I could see the inner yard from there, but I
only saw what looked like brick storerooms.
レンガで出来た物置みたいなもん
とにかく お墓じゃなかったよ
At any rate, they weren’t gravestones.
出た 出た やっぱり
覚のホラ話だったんじゃん
See? I knew it was one of your tall tales.
俺は ホントに聞いたんだってば！
和貴園の怖い話なら まだ あるぜ
I didn’t make this up!
I know plenty of other scary stuff about Harmony School.
Yeah, yeah.
はいはい 怖い 怖い あ～ 怖っ！
ちょっと もう やめてよ！
Scary, scary.
Hey, cut it out already!
What more is there?
それって 何の話？
Mamoru! I said I don’t want to hear any more!
守！ もう聞きたくないって
言ってるでしょ！
But…
でも…
There’s another person who saw
something scary in Harmony School.
和貴園でさ もう１つ
怖いものを見た人がいるって
ものすごく大きな 猫の影
A giant cat shadow.
それって ネコダマシ？
You mean a Copycat?
It looks like the Copycats come to school a lot.
ネコダマシって
よく学校に出るらしいぜ
何でなの？
決まってるじゃない！
Why?
Isn’t it obvious? They’re after the students.
子供を狙ってるからよ！
季節は秋… 夕方くらいに
出ることが多いんだって
It was fall.
The time of year when they often wander about at sunset.
家まで来ることもあるんだけど
大抵は 真夜中で…
They sometimes go to your homes,
but usually in the dead of the night—
Stop it!
やめて！
早季？
Saki?
What’s wrong?
どうしたの？
ねえ 和貴園を 早く卒業したから
偉いってことじゃないのよ
Okay?
Graduating from Harmony School early doesn’t mean you’re better or anything.
呪力の強さや 質にも
全然 関係ないわ
It has nothing to do with the power or quality of your Cantus.
知ってる？ 私も お父さんも
そんなに早い方じゃなかったのよ
Did I tell you?
Your father and I took a long time too.
いちばん最後でも
なかったんでしょ？
But you weren’t the last ones, right?
それは そうだけど… でもね
Well… yes, but…
もし卒業できなかったら？
What if I don’t graduate at all?
Is it true that a Copycat comes for you if you don’t graduate?
卒業できなかったら ネコダマシが
迎えに来るって ホント？
バカねえ ネコダマシなんて
この世にいないの
Come on. There are no such things as Copycats.
もうすぐ 大人になるっていうのに
You’ll soon become an adult, so don’t say that or people will laugh at you.
そんなこと言ってると
笑われちゃうわよ
But I saw one.
でも 私 見たの
Don’t be silly!
何 言ってるの ただの錯覚よ
You were imagining it.
見たのよ
I saw one.
早季？ 早季？
Saki? Saki?
あっ
大丈夫？
Are you okay?
Yeah.
Get a grip.
バカだな お前 こんなん
和貴園の頃から 有名なウワサだろ
This story was real popular back in Harmony School.
今さら 怖がって どうすんだよ
Why would it scare you now?
うるさい！ 覚は黙っててよ！
Shut up! Shut up, Satoru!
なんだよ…
何 本気で怒ってんだよ
What?
Why are you so mad?
What’s wrong?
どうしたの？
あ… 何でもない
Nothing…
ねえ もう帰らないと ね？
Well, we should head home now.
Yeah.
ネコダマシに会っても
知らないからね
Not my problem if a Copycat finds you!
Have you seen one?
見たことあるの？
Of course not.
ねえよ 見たら 食われてるよ
It would’ve eaten me if I had.
I thought they don’t attack unless provoked?
最初は 襲わないとか
言ってなかった？
僕も聞いた
I heard so too.
Who told you?
誰が言ったの？
誰だっけ？
I don’t remember.
じゃあね
See you!
Yeah, bye-bye!
うん バイバ～イ
See you!
またな
早季～！
Saki!
How’s Sage Academy, Saki?
おっ 早季 全人学級は どうだ？
うん 面白い… かな？
Interesting, I guess.
｢かな｣って 何だよ
はっきりしないなあ
You guess?
Is it or is it not?
まだ 入ったばっかりだから
よく分からないんじゃない？
She only just started, so she wouldn’t really know yet.
Yeah, it’s so-so.
うん でも まあまあ
I’m so worried.
心配だわ… このまま でも…
At this rate, you know—
Wait!
まあ 待って
君が そんなに気をもんでたら
If you worry so much, you’ll make her feel uneasy too.
かえって 悪影響を与えるよ
どんな授業をやってるんだ？
What are classes like?
カードでピラミッド作ったり…
砂絵とか
We made a pyramid with cards and drew some things in sand.
そうかあ お父さんたちの頃と
あまり変わらないな
I see.
That’s pretty much what we did back then.
お父さんは イタズラが好きでね～
Your father loved to play pranks.
He threw haythatcher eggs at
the statue in front of the school.
学校の銅像に カヤノスヅクリの
たまごをぶつけて
校長だった 無瞋上人に
いっぱい怒られたのよ
Priest Mushin, who was the principal back then, gave him hell for it.
That was ages ago.
いつの話 してるんだ
でも このままじゃ…
But at this rate…
ねえ そろそろ 教育委員会が
動く頃じゃない？
Don’t you think the Board of Education will act soon?
I don’t know.
分からない…
Trying to influence the Board from the library is really hard.
図書館から 教育委員会に
影響を行使するのは 難しいのよ
あなたは 決裁権者なんだから
You’re the Judge.
Couldn’t you do something about it?
その気になれば
何とかできるでしょう？
委員会は独立だよ
私の職権では 調べようがないし
The Board is independent.
I can’t investigate them with my authority.
まして 早季の父親という立場では
そんな意見…
Not to mention my opinions are moot since I’m Saki’s father—
I don’t want to lose any more of my children!
私 もう子供をなくすのは
イヤよ！
Quiet down!
声が大きいよ！
But Saki said she saw a Tainted Cat!
だって 早季は
｢不浄猫を見た｣って言ったのよ！
気のせいかもしれない
Maybe she was imagining it!
What if she wasn’t?!
もし本当だったら どうするのよ！
早季 早季？
Saki? Saki?
どうした？
What’s wrong?
無事に祝霊は来たし
清浄寺にも行ったし
The Spirit of Blessing came to you, you went to the Temple of Purity, and you’ve begun studying at Sage Academy.
全人学級の授業も始まったし…
お母さん ホッとしてるのよ
I’m so relieved.
｢ホッとしてる｣？
Relieved?
I don’t want to lose any more of my children!
私 もう子供をなくすのは
イヤよ！
Relieved? What do you mean?
｢ホッとしてる｣って
どういう意味なの？
Isn’t that obvious?
そりゃあ
ホッとして当たり前だろう
お父さんたちだって
祝霊が遅くて
Our parents were worried too
when the spirits were taking too long.
親に 心配されたからなあ
いいか 早季
我々 人間は 呪力を使える
Listen, Saki.
We humans can use Cantus.
But it’s a small, insignificant power.
だけど それは
微々たるものでしかない
だから 大事にしていかないと
そのためには よ～く…
That’s why we have to treasure it.
For that reaso—
ごちそうさま
Thanks for the food.
それから 数日後
A few days later, Amano Reiko vanished from the school.
天野麗子の姿が
ＳＨＩＮＳＥＫＡＩ
ＹＯＲＩ
学校から消えた
ＳＨＩＮＳＥＫＡＩ
ＹＯＲＩ
Nakisou na aoringo kakaeteru mune no oku
泣きそうな青リンゴ  抱えてる胸の奥
In my chest, I carry a green apple that wets my eyes
Korogatte tsuyogatte
転がって  強がって
I fall over yet pretend to be strong
Kyuukutsu na sora niramu
窮屈な空睨む
I glower at the sky and it seems to suffocate me
Unmei ni juujun ni
運命に従順に
Do I look like I'd wait quietly
Jukusu no wo matsu mon ka
熟すのを待つもんか
For destiny to ripen it?
Sen no kaze
千の風
The winds
Agaite sakende
あがいて  叫んで
I struggle and scream
Fuke fuke
吹け吹け
Blow and blow
Watashi wa shabondama
わたしはしゃぼん玉
I'm a soap bubble
Soredemo shinjiteru
それでも信じてる
And still I have faith
Yokisenu arashi ni
予期せぬ  嵐に
In a sudden storm
Joushou shite kakou shite
上昇して  下降して
I rise and fall
Aragau shabondama
あらがうしゃぼん玉
I fight, soap bubble that I am
Soredemo ikiteku
それでも生きてく
And still I live on
Hajikeru shunkan niji hanate
弾ける瞬間  虹、放て
I make a rainbow when I burst
少年は
自らの頭の良さを誇るあまり
The boy mocked all things around him so as to glorify his own intellect.
あらゆるものを
小バカにしていたのだ
Pride plants the seeds of bad karma.
傲慢は 業の種をまく
Solitude brings the seeds of bad karma to fruit.
孤独は 業の苗床になる